Hello and welcome to the first lecture of computer
architecture for everybody. In this lecture,
we're going to talk about the origins of data
computing lines, straight lines and curves and
numbers and how our obsession with measuring our
real world uh led to eventually computing. So,
we're going to cover a number of different
topics. We're going to talk about measuring
the solar system and how looking up at the night
sky and trying to understand how the night sky
works. Uh continuous physical analog computing
using things like uh slide rules and how we did
multiplication using slide rules back in the day.
talk about digital physical devices such as like
even a a clicky pen is kind of a digital physical
device and that it's it's it's not digital but
it has two distinct states and it's stable in
both states and that's digital. So pen clocks
uh another digital physical device is one of these
little clicky things that people used to calculate
their grocery bill as they were shopping before we
had hand calculators. The other thing that people
did is before we had hand calculators that could
conveniently calculate sin and cosine, we had
these really big books that had tables of numbers
so that you could look up sin and cosine in those
books. And so we'll eventually move from there on
to human computers which is iteration by lot rooms
full of people doing calculations or the Babbage
difference engine which was steam powered that
could calculate polynomials. Then we move into
electro-mechanical computers like the Bomba or
pinball machines. And then eventually we end up on
the first electronic computer using tubes called
Colossus at Bletchley Park. And so that is leads
us to the beginning of the electronic computer
age. Now I really want to tell you that this is
not a class about mathematics. Numbers are kind of
the obsession in the beginning because computation
and numbers were a big deal. But if you take my C
class, C programming for everybody, I talk a lot
about how everything in computing changed in 1978.
There's other important moments where things
changed in a dramatic way. But before 1978,
a lot of computing had to do with numbers. Numbers
were the focus. There was no internet. There was
no email. Computers were large, filled a room.
They were very expensive. Millions and millions
of dollars. Then you use them to do numeric
calculations that were otherwise impractical. But
after 1978, computers got smaller and faster and
the internet kind of came along and people stopped
doing numbers as the main thing the computers did.
Of course, computers are still good at numbers,
but they're no longer the main thing that we
do. We do it mostly for communication and data,
artificial intelligence, and those kinds of
things. Although numbers are important part
of artificial intelligence but in general the
arc of computers and computing sort of starts
and for its early early phases it's all about the
numbers and so there's a few math examples but
I'll explain all the math where it needs to be.
So the big problem that we humans are trying to
solve with numeric calculations and formulas etc
is the notion of the fact that light travels in
straight lines. And so when we see things with our
eyes we see a world that seems to be straight line
but everything else in that world is moving in a
curved path. So for example, if I were to throw
a softball to you, that softball would follow a
parabola. And so through millennia of evolution,
our eyes have learned to calculate parabas.
Otherwise, we would not be able to throw and
catch a ball. And yes, I'm using a sports analogy
right now. Meaning that how does one see a ball
and hit it with a bat in a game of wheelchair
softball? How does that happen? But really, a lot
of what we do in sports today is something that
used to have to do with survival, gathering food,
uh fighting, other kinds of things that were
part of our survival. So this notion that we
are people with eyes that see things in
lines perceiving a world of curves. So
one of the first fascinations with the world
of curves has to do with stargazing. [Music]
Everybody who sits outside at night and looks
up into a clear night sky with various patterns
of stars slowly moving around. It's natural
to wonder exactly what's up there. And humans
throughout all of our history have, you know, come
up with explanations for why the stars were doing
what they were doing. One of the things that we
could look at and measure a little more easily
than other things in terms of the motion of the
skies is the sunrise and the sunset of the well
the rise and the set of the moon and the stars
and the sun because they changed but then after
a while if you watch them and measure them they
change in a very very specific pattern. And so
here I'm showing you a picture of the a series
of sunsets that I constructed underneath the Meno
Bridge in northern Michigan. I took this picture
in August and there one of those suns is real.
The rest of them are sort of made up suns, but you
could at this point use the motion of the sunset
against the horizon as something that would tell
you about the season of the year. And it turns
out that tracking these seasons has been important
for all of our cultures for 10,000 years. And the
reason is is the location of the sunset tells
us about the weather. When are the rains going
to happen? When should we plant crops? When is it
dangerous? And there's a song that we in the state
of Michigan of a certain age called the wreck of
the Edmund Fitzgerald that talks about how when
you are in Lake Superior, no matter how large
of a boat you have, the gales of November will
come after you. And this was a gigantic boat,
modern boat. And there was enough wind in the
November storm that sunk the Edmund Fitzgerald.
And it was quite shocking because in the 1970s we
thought technology would solve everything.
And so, but this is a good example of how
not knowing what time of year you're going to do
something, set out on a long journey or whatever,
could have some significant consequences. And if
we look back in history, there are many artifacts
across many cultures that are based on tracking
the sun. Calendars of various kinds. Some are
tracking the sun. some of the sun and the moon and
they are solar calendars of one form or another
that look at the the sunrise and sun sunset
angles from various places. One of the older
and most sophisticated ones is Stonehenge. Now
these were all over the world right um just in
all cultures of various sizes and forms etc. And
so I've listed on this slide some of the various
times that different cultures invented various
things having to do with the sun. And if you
look at some of those dates, you're like, whoa,
Stonehenge was pretty far uh pretty long time
ago compared to some of these other things. And
so we in the modern world, we have our fun time
with modern hinges. If you go to a certain street
in Manhattan on a certain day at a certain time,
you see this beam of light. And I'm sure that's
what fascinated early people as they built these
things was that you know the light seems random
and then all of a sudden like like a laser beam
whoosh the light comes down this long corridor and
in the case of Manhattan it's like a mile or so
and the light just bursts through and there's one
in Chicago where again you stand at a particular
location and the sun the these are sunrises uh
comes right to you in an otherwise dark thing
and it again you could imagine Imagine that early
people would see this this burst of the sun into a
dark location is somehow a very mystical moment
and a very mystical event. And and Stonehenge,
a lot of folks think that Stonehenge was there
to decide when to have certain celebrations,
right? So, a spring celebration, a summer
solstice celebration, etc. And so, at the bottom,
you can see a what I'll call a Dr. Chuck's commute
henge where I just happened to be driving in a
while ago. And the sun was at a perfect angle that
it c came up underneath uh it was just rising and
it came up underneath a overpass. And I just
kind of clicked the button on my cell phone so
that I could capture this moment. Again, that's
a that's a moment that has to be location, time,
time, day of year, and then you could see that
if you stood there. And again, I don't really
particularly celebrate or go I don't go down every
fall to try to catch this sunrise underneath this
bridge, but you get the idea that you're like,
"Whoa, this this object in this in the sky was
moving randomly." And now all of a sudden today,
it's shooting right at me through a little tiny
hole. And you can you can kind of imagine that the
builders of Stonehenge were quite interested in
the moment that the sun would appear and burst
onto them. And if you were standing somewhere,
it'd be dark and then you would be like a beam of
direct light would be on you. And so it's pretty
exciting. Now, there was a lot of iteration
in several kind of concentric structures at
Stonehenge that were built between 5,100 years
ago and 3,600 years ago. And so to some degree,
you could imagine that by the time they were
done with this, they had a pretty good sense
of where the sun rose and sun set as it moved
across the horizon around Stonehenge. And you
can think of it as like it's a data table that
has been tracking the sun. Had been tracking the
sun for 2500 years. So up next we're going to
talk about moving things. Everything up to now
I've talked about is just like measuring the
sun, a sun dial. But up next we'll talk about
uh analog devices with gears and pulleys etc that
attempt to do some computations. And we'll stick
with in the beginning the obsession with the
location of the sun. [Music] [Applause] [Music]